<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Leonard Chau - Portfolio &amp; Engineering Blog</title><link href="https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/</id><updated>2025-02-10T10:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Welcome to My Engineering Blog</title><link href="https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/posts/2025/02/10/welcome-to-my-engineering-blog/" rel="alternate"/><published>2025-02-10T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-10T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Leonard Chau</name></author><id>tag:dairyking98.github.io,2025-02-10:/Portfolio/posts/2025/02/10/welcome-to-my-engineering-blog/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my personal portfolio and engineering blog. This is where I&amp;#8217;ll share my projects, thoughts, and&amp;nbsp;experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my engineering blog and&amp;nbsp;portfolio!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site is built with &lt;a href="https://getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator powered by Python. I&amp;#8217;ll be using this space&amp;nbsp;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share engineering projects and technical&amp;nbsp;insights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document my learning&amp;nbsp;journey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Showcase portfolio&amp;nbsp;work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write about topics that interest&amp;nbsp;me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-to-expect"&gt;What to&amp;nbsp;Expect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll find posts&amp;nbsp;covering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/strong&gt;: Development practices, tools, and&amp;nbsp;techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Projects&lt;/strong&gt;: Detailed write-ups of personal and professional&amp;nbsp;projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorials&lt;/strong&gt;: Step-by-step guides and&amp;nbsp;how-tos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;: Reflections on technology and&amp;nbsp;engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="getting-started"&gt;Getting&amp;nbsp;Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to explore the site using the navigation menu. You&amp;nbsp;can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browse posts by &lt;a href="/tags.html"&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;View the &lt;a href="/archives.html"&gt;archives&lt;/a&gt; for all&amp;nbsp;posts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check out my &lt;a href="/projects"&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for visiting, and I hope you find something interesting&amp;nbsp;here!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"/><category term="portfolio"/><category term="intro"/></entry><entry><title>Open-Ended Experiment: Tensile Testing of Acrylic with Geometric Discontinuities</title><link href="https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/posts/2024/12/20/open-ended-experiment-tensile-testing-of-acrylic-with-geometric-discontinuities/" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-12-20T09:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T09:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Leonard Chau</name></author><id>tag:dairyking98.github.io,2024-12-20:/Portfolio/posts/2024/12/20/open-ended-experiment-tensile-testing-of-acrylic-with-geometric-discontinuities/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Investigated how cast acrylic specimens with holes and notches respond to tensile loading using Instron testing and stress concentration&amp;nbsp;analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ENGR&lt;/span&gt; 302 – Experimental Analysis at San Francisco State University culminated in an open-ended lab where my teammates (Tom Boivin, Driss Hakkou, Denis Steffen) and I characterized how geometric discontinuities influence the tensile performance of 1/4-inch cast acrylic. We modeled and fabricated “dog bone” specimens with circular, notched, square, and diamond cut-outs, then compared their behavior against a control sample to understand how stress concentration factors translate into real&amp;nbsp;failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="project-overview"&gt;Project&amp;nbsp;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt; quantify the impact of different discontinuity geometries on acrylic tensile strength and ductility, and compare the findings against theoretical stress concentration&amp;nbsp;predictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My focus:&lt;/strong&gt; coordinating specimen preparation, verifying the Instron 3369 test program, and consolidating the load–elongation data exported from Bluehill Universal into a clean dataset for team&amp;nbsp;analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course context:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ENGR&lt;/span&gt; 302 — Experimental Analysis, Fall 2024 (Instructor: Dr. Ed&amp;nbsp;Cheng).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="experimental-setup"&gt;Experimental&amp;nbsp;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used an Instron 3369 tensile test frame with a 50 kN load cell and threaded side-action grips to maintain alignment and avoid slippage. Each test ran at 2 in/min while Bluehill Universal logged force and displacement. An initial calibration sweep checked the load cell and grip tension before every pair of&amp;nbsp;specimens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specimens were laser-cut from McMaster-Carr cast acrylic sheet&amp;nbsp;(&lt;code&gt;4615T47&lt;/code&gt;), sanded to remove machining marks, and measured to capture true cross-sectional areas. Control blanks retained the full gauge width, while the discontinuity specimens reduced the critical area to approximately 29.5 mm². Detailed dimensions and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; sketches are included in the source&amp;nbsp;report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-findings"&gt;Key&amp;nbsp;Findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Control baseline:&lt;/strong&gt; yielded at 11.1 MPa—roughly 80% lower than the manufacturer’s 55 MPa specification—highlighting how processing and environmental factors can degrade acrylic&amp;nbsp;strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circular vs. notched specimens:&lt;/strong&gt; yielded at 18.96 MPa (Kt ≈ 1.71) and 21.56 MPa (Kt ≈ 1.94), respectively. The rounded notch distributed stress slightly better than the through-hole, aligning closely with handbook&amp;nbsp;predictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharp corners matter:&lt;/strong&gt; square and diamond cut-outs experienced brittle failures at 17.25 MPa and 20.51 MPa with minimal elongation (≤1.76 mm), confirming how angular geometry acts like pre-existing&amp;nbsp;cracks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ductility loss:&lt;/strong&gt; control specimens stretched to 10.2 mm before fracture, whereas discontinuity samples fractured almost immediately after yielding, showing how stress raisers strip away energy absorption&amp;nbsp;capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="theoretical-vs-experimental-snapshot"&gt;Theoretical vs. Experimental&amp;nbsp;Snapshot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Specimen Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Theoretical Yield Stress (MPa)†&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Experimental Yield Stress (MPa)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ratio (Actual ÷ Theoretical)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Control&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11 (baseline)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Circular Hole&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23.70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.80 (Kt ≈ 1.71)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Notched&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19.74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.09 (Kt ≈ 1.94)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;†Derived using control yield stress as the nominal reference and handbook stress concentration factors.&lt;br&gt;
Note: We could not locate reliable theoretical data for the laser-cut square and diamond geometries—those specimens are discussed purely from experimental&amp;nbsp;observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="experimental-metrics-overview"&gt;Experimental Metrics&amp;nbsp;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Specimen Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Yield Force (N)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Yield Stress (MPa)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Ultimate Stress (MPa)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Fracture Stress (MPa)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Max Elongation (mm)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Modulus (MPa)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Control&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;750&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;11.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;57.04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;51.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;10.20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,743&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Circular Hole&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;580&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;18.96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;50.27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;50.27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1.63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4,116.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Notched&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;625&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;21.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;71.63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;71.57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4,098.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Square Hole&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;17.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;54.77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;54.77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1.76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3,483&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Diamond Hole&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;20.51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.89&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4,478&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional&amp;nbsp;context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-sectional area:&lt;/strong&gt; control blanks averaged 67.51 mm²; all discontinuity specimens clustered around 29–31&amp;nbsp;mm².&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elongation at yield:&lt;/strong&gt; ranged from 0.39–0.55 mm, reinforcing the brittle response once discontinuities were&amp;nbsp;introduced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stress concentration factors:&lt;/strong&gt; experimentally back-calculated Kt values were 1.00 (control), 1.71 (circle), and 1.94 (notch); the square and diamond data did not yield stable Kt values because the failure location varied&amp;nbsp;specimen-to-specimen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="discussion-and-recommendations"&gt;Discussion and&amp;nbsp;Recommendations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The close agreement between theoretical and experimental stress concentration factors for simple shapes validated our analytical approach. However, the scatter in the square and diamond data underlined the limits of handbook solutions for complex geometries. We&amp;nbsp;recommended:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowing the crosshead speed to 0.5 in/min for more stable strain measurements on brittle&amp;nbsp;plastics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polishing laser-cut edges to reduce micro-crack initiation&amp;nbsp;sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extending the study with finite element analysis to visualize stress fields around sharp&amp;nbsp;corners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeating the experiment across temperatures to capture acrylic’s sensitivity to cold-induced&amp;nbsp;embrittlement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons&amp;nbsp;Learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Material datasheet values can diverge dramatically from lab-prepared specimens; surface finish and fabrication technique&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precise dimensional metrology is essential when small area changes drive stress&amp;nbsp;calculations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capturing full test context (fixture setup, calibration steps, environmental notes) makes post-lab analysis and reporting far&amp;nbsp;easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="source-document"&gt;Source&amp;nbsp;Document&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2024/engr302/OEE-Final-Report-12-20-24.pdf"&gt;Open-Ended Experiment Report (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Completed December 2024 for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ENGR&lt;/span&gt; 302 — Experimental Analysis (Professor Ed&amp;nbsp;Cheng).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="School Projects"/><category term="materials-testing"/><category term="mechanical-engineering"/><category term="stress-analysis"/><category term="school-project"/></entry><entry><title>Analog Voltmeter Clock - Time and Environmental Monitor</title><link href="https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/posts/2024/12/15/analog-voltmeter-clock-time-and-environmental-monitor/" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-12-15T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Leonard Chau</name></author><id>tag:dairyking98.github.io,2024-12-15:/Portfolio/posts/2024/12/15/analog-voltmeter-clock-time-and-environmental-monitor/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A unique clock project combining analog voltmeters with environmental monitoring, featuring custom 3D-printed enclosure and Arduino-based control&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This project was completed for Assignment 4 in Fall 2024, under Professor Jonathan Song. The challenge was to design and build a device that displays time using analog voltmeters, with the added functionality of monitoring pressure, temperature, and&amp;nbsp;humidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="project-overview"&gt;Project&amp;nbsp;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The device I built is a clock combined with a pressure, temperature, and humidity monitor using analog voltmeters for an engaging and unique display. The analog voltmeters feature custom legends that indicate the current hour, minute, and second, or pressure, temperature, and humidity on a graduated scale. I was inspired by the idea of using analog displays to show time, which has a classic and visually engaging aesthetic. To further challenge myself, I integrated environmental monitoring features, making the device&amp;nbsp;multi-functional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All components and the encoder knob assembly are securely fastened to a custom 3D-printed enclosure made of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt; on an Ender 5 printer. Time adjustments are made using a homemade rotary encoder and a button. The display toggles with a short press of the&amp;nbsp;button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="physical-design"&gt;Physical&amp;nbsp;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the physical design, I aimed to create something large and unique—a device that would instill curiosity at first glance. The analog voltmeters and vintage embossed labels provide a sense of nostalgia. The oversized rotary encoder is a deliberate design choice, serving both functional and educational purposes. The method of function of an incremental rotary encoder can now be felt, seen, and heard. It offers a satisfying, hands-on experience and acts as a demonstration tool to illustrate the inner workings of a rotary&amp;nbsp;encoder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analog voltmeter&amp;#8217;s original 0-30V graduated display was modified with custom-designed and printed legends that indicate:
- &lt;strong&gt;Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: 0-12
- &lt;strong&gt;Minutes and Seconds&lt;/strong&gt;: 0-60
- &lt;strong&gt;Pressure&lt;/strong&gt;: 950-1030 hPa
- &lt;strong&gt;Relative Humidity&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;0-100%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These values were chosen as the range at which this device is estimated to function. The voltmeters, originally rated for 30V, had to be further modified to operate at 5V by removing their internal resistors and installing adjustable potentiometers for&amp;nbsp;calibration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="system-architecture"&gt;System&amp;nbsp;Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DS3231&lt;/span&gt; real-time clock module (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTC&lt;/span&gt;) is used to keep accurate time and maintain the time even when the Arduino is fully powered off, thanks to an external watch battery. It communicates with the Arduino via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;I2C&lt;/span&gt; protocol. The current time provided by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTC&lt;/span&gt; is obtained constantly and stored as variables in the&amp;nbsp;Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BMP180&lt;/span&gt; pressure sensor also communicates via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;I2C&lt;/span&gt;, and the current pressure is stored as a variable. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DHT22&lt;/span&gt; humidity sensor operates via pulse-width modulated input, which is handled by a library, and its variable is also&amp;nbsp;stored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time and environmental variables are converted to integers in the range of 0 to 255 to provide pulse-width modulated outputs for the voltmeters. When the display mode is set to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt;, the voltmeters display the current hour, minute, and second at quarter-second intervals to provide for a sweeping second hand, and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HOURS&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MINUTES&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SECONDS&lt;/span&gt; LEDs remain on. When the display mode is set to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PTH&lt;/span&gt; (pressure, temperature, and humidity), the voltmeters display the current pressure, temperature, and humidity, and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PRESSURE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TEMPERATURE&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HUMIDITY&lt;/span&gt; LEDs remain&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="user-interface"&gt;User&amp;nbsp;Interface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The display mode is toggleable via a short press of a user-interaction arcade button. Upon a long press of the arcade button, a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHANGE&lt;/span&gt; mode is entered, in which the rotary encoder is used to select the new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HOUR&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MINUTE&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SECOND&lt;/span&gt;. This is indicated by a blinking corresponding &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; and isolated operation of the selected voltmeter. A new value is confirmed by pressing the arcade button until the last parameter, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SECONDS&lt;/span&gt;, has been updated, returning to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIME&lt;/span&gt; display&amp;nbsp;mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rotary encoder operates on two input signals that are treated as interrupts, performing interrupt service routines (ISRs) when their signal values change, providing for a responsive and effective incremental rotary&amp;nbsp;encoder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="components-and-materials"&gt;Components and&amp;nbsp;Materials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The device is built using the following&amp;nbsp;components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arduino Nano&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;(microcontroller)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two limit switches&lt;/strong&gt; (used for rotary encoder&amp;nbsp;input)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One arcade button&lt;/strong&gt; (for toggling the display and time&amp;nbsp;adjustment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DHT22&lt;/span&gt; sensor&lt;/strong&gt; (for temperature and humidity&amp;nbsp;sensing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BMP180&lt;/span&gt; sensor&lt;/strong&gt; (for pressure&amp;nbsp;sensing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Six 6V LEDs&lt;/strong&gt; (for illumination and visual&amp;nbsp;feedback)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DS3231&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Real-Time Clock) module (for accurate&amp;nbsp;timekeeping)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three analog voltmeters&lt;/strong&gt; (to display time and environmental&amp;nbsp;data)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three 5kΩ potentiometers&lt;/strong&gt; (for analog voltmeter&amp;nbsp;calibration)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D-printed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt; enclosure&lt;/strong&gt; (custom-designed&amp;nbsp;housing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various resistors, wires, and mounting&amp;nbsp;hardware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-features"&gt;Key&amp;nbsp;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dual Display Modes&lt;/strong&gt;: Toggle between time display and environmental&amp;nbsp;monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quarter-Second Updates&lt;/strong&gt;: Smooth sweeping second hand using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PWM&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;interpolation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Custom Calibrated Voltmeters&lt;/strong&gt;: Modified from 30V to 5V operation with custom&amp;nbsp;legends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homemade Rotary Encoder&lt;/strong&gt;: Built from limit switches for educational&amp;nbsp;demonstration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D-Printed Enclosure&lt;/strong&gt;: Custom-designed housing for all&amp;nbsp;components&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-Time Clock&lt;/strong&gt;: Maintains accurate time even when powered&amp;nbsp;off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="technical-implementation"&gt;Technical&amp;nbsp;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Arduino code handles:
- Reading time from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DS3231&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTC&lt;/span&gt; module
- Reading environmental data from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BMP180&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DHT22&lt;/span&gt; sensors
- Converting values to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PWM&lt;/span&gt; signals (0-255) for voltmeter control
- Managing rotary encoder interrupts for time adjustment
- Button press detection (short press for mode toggle, long press for time adjustment)
- &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; control for visual feedback
- Quarter-second interpolation for smooth second hand&amp;nbsp;movement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="development-process"&gt;Development&amp;nbsp;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project involved several key development&amp;nbsp;steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptual Design&lt;/strong&gt;: Initial idea for using analog voltmeters as&amp;nbsp;displays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Component Selection&lt;/strong&gt;: Choosing appropriate sensors and&amp;nbsp;microcontroller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voltmeter Modification&lt;/strong&gt;: Removing internal resistors and adding potentiometers for 5V&amp;nbsp;operation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Custom Legend Design&lt;/strong&gt;: Creating and printing custom scales for each&amp;nbsp;voltmeter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D Enclosure Design&lt;/strong&gt;: Designing and printing the housing in Fusion&amp;nbsp;360&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arduino Programming&lt;/strong&gt;: Implementing the control logic and sensor&amp;nbsp;interfaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calibration&lt;/strong&gt;: Adjusting potentiometers to match voltmeter readings with actual&amp;nbsp;values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testing and Refinement&lt;/strong&gt;: Iterative testing to ensure accuracy and&amp;nbsp;reliability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons&amp;nbsp;Learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project taught me valuable lessons about:
- Interfacing multiple sensors with Arduino (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;I2C&lt;/span&gt; and digital protocols)
- &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PWM&lt;/span&gt; signal generation and calibration
- Real-time clock integration and time management
- Rotary encoder implementation using interrupts
- 3D printing considerations for electronics enclosures
- Analog display calibration and modification
- User interface design for embedded&amp;nbsp;systems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="source-documents"&gt;Source&amp;nbsp;Documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following documents are available for&amp;nbsp;reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2024/clock-project/Clock-Report.pdf"&gt;Clock Report&lt;/a&gt; - Complete project report with detailed design, implementation, and&amp;nbsp;analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2024/clock-project/Assignment-4-Project-Idea.pdf"&gt;Assignment 4 Project Idea&lt;/a&gt; - Initial project proposal and&amp;nbsp;concept&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2024/clock-project/Arduino-Clock-Code.md"&gt;Arduino Clock Code&lt;/a&gt; - Complete source code with detailed&amp;nbsp;comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2024/clock-project/Clock-Presentation.pdf"&gt;Clock Presentation&lt;/a&gt; - Project presentation&amp;nbsp;slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This project was completed in December 2024 for Assignment 4 (Professor Jonathan Song) as part of my academic&amp;nbsp;coursework.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="School Projects"/><category term="arduino"/><category term="electronics"/><category term="embedded-systems"/><category term="sensors"/><category term="3d-printing"/><category term="school-project"/></entry><entry><title>CAD Project - Self-Propelled Wall Leaper</title><link href="https://dairyking98.github.io/Portfolio/posts/2022/11/29/cad-project-self-propelled-wall-leaper/" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-11-29T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-29T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Leonard Chau</name></author><id>tag:dairyking98.github.io,2022-11-29:/Portfolio/posts/2022/11/29/cad-project-self-propelled-wall-leaper/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A detailed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; design project from my Intro to Engineering course, where I designed and built a self-propelled device that launches over a 3-foot wall using rubber band power and 3D printed&amp;nbsp;components.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This project was completed for my Intro to Engineering course in November 2022, under Professor Khandani. The challenge was to create a device from scratch that is self-propelled and launches from one point to another 8 feet away while overcoming a 3-foot vertical height in the&amp;nbsp;center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="video-demonstration"&gt;Video&amp;nbsp;Demonstration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YUEf5KbRb5A" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="1-define-the-problem"&gt;1: Define the&amp;nbsp;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="problem-statement"&gt;Problem&amp;nbsp;Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to create a device from scratch that is self-propelled, and launches from one point to another 8 feet away while overcoming a 3-foot vertical height in the&amp;nbsp;center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="criteria-for-success"&gt;Criteria for&amp;nbsp;Success&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The criteria I wanted to impose upon a successful device design are the&amp;nbsp;following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplicity/complexity of design&lt;/strong&gt; - The device should be relatively simple and easy to understand the methods of operation and how trajectory is achieved. Parts should be easy to&amp;nbsp;obtain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predictability of travel/consistency/repeatability&lt;/strong&gt; - Trajectory of the device should be almost the same with minimal variation between&amp;nbsp;launches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ease/difficulty of triggering mechanism&lt;/strong&gt; - The device should be triggered without creating a large disturbance from the hands triggering it. A device sensitive to hand movements or difficult to trigger may not have an intended&amp;nbsp;trajectory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build time&lt;/strong&gt; - The device should not take long to assemble and modify if&amp;nbsp;necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safety&lt;/strong&gt; - The device should be relatively safe to operate. Minimize sharps, projectiles, accidental&amp;nbsp;triggers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D printability&lt;/strong&gt; - The device should be easily 3D modeled and printed. I am very familiar with 3D prototyping and printing, so I will feel most comfortable and efficient working with 3D printed&amp;nbsp;parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2-gather-pertinent-information"&gt;2: Gather Pertinent&amp;nbsp;Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device must travel together with nothing remaining at the launch point, and cannot be thrown from&amp;nbsp;hands.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device may be powered mechanically or electrically. Chemical explosives, living creatures, remote control devices, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CO2&lt;/span&gt; cartridges, or pressurized gas or liquid tanks made of metal or plastic may not be&amp;nbsp;used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device must leap over a wall 3 feet high, starting 4 feet away from the base of the wall, and targeting 4 feet away from the base of the other side of the&amp;nbsp;wall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device must land as close to the target line as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device must be made from&amp;nbsp;scratch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device must not expand or contract after&amp;nbsp;landing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device has only two opportunities to leap for the official&amp;nbsp;test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The device is restricted to a total cost of&amp;nbsp;$20.00.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="3-generate-multiple-solutions"&gt;3: Generate Multiple&amp;nbsp;Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design-1-helicopter-like-device"&gt;Design 1: Helicopter-like&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubber band powered propeller shaft connected to rigid lightweight frame with fins to counter the rotation induced by the propeller spinning. Release of trigger would be letting go of wound up propeller and device by&amp;nbsp;hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design-2-stick-leaper-device"&gt;Design 2: Stick-leaper&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubber-band powered scissor-like linkages to propel mass at a high velocity to build momentum and carry the entire device over the wall. Mass is linearly propelled. Release of trigger would be balancing rubber band snap position at tension right before tipping point, and gentle push with finger past tipping point to trigger the release of tension and cause snapping together of&amp;nbsp;linkages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design-3-mousetrap-catapult-device"&gt;Design 3: Mousetrap-catapult&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mousetrap spring-powered self-catapulting system to fling mass towards trajectory over the wall to carry the catapult with it. Similar to the stick-leaper device, but mass is propelled somewhat angularly. Release of trigger would be some sort of hair&amp;nbsp;trigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design-4-blimp-balloon-device"&gt;Design 4: Blimp-balloon&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubber band powered propeller shaft attached to a helium balloon, counterweighted just enough so that it almost floats through the air with the same average density as air. Release of the trigger would be done by&amp;nbsp;hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design-5-spring-propelled-javelin-device"&gt;Design 5: Spring-propelled javelin&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A javelin-like shaft is attached to and protruding through a spring. Spring is held in hands and the shaft is pulled back, aimed, and released. Or; shaft is propped on the ground and angled towards the desired trajectory. Mass on spring is pulled back and released. Velocity of mass generates momentum for the device to leap over the&amp;nbsp;wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="4-analyze-and-select-a-solution"&gt;4: Analyze and Select a&amp;nbsp;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="decision-matrix"&gt;Decision&amp;nbsp;Matrix&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Criteria&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Weight %&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design 2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design 3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design 4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Design 5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Safety&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Predictability&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Build Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trigger&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Simplicity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3D Printability&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;100&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;320&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;800&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;350&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;340&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;610&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design 2, the stick-leaper (in bold), is the design that has the most weight in the decision matrix&amp;nbsp;above.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design 1 seems very unpredictable, and weight dependent. Design 2 seems most logical. It looks relatively simple to 3D model and print. Design 3 may break the Professor&amp;#8217;s rules, as it is not made completely from scratch. Design 4 seems very unpredictable and weight dependent. Design 5 seems like it would require a very strong spring, or break the Professor&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="5-test-and-implement-the-solution"&gt;5: Test and Implement the&amp;nbsp;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began designing with Autodesk Fusion 360, which I am most familiar with and use to create models for 3D printing. I designed keeping in mind that my parts would be 3D printed, and thus the geometry must be accommodating for 3D&amp;nbsp;printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="first-prototype"&gt;First&amp;nbsp;Prototype&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first prototype was made exactly how I envisioned it, and I quickly found issues that presented themselves and would impede efficient operation of the&amp;nbsp;leaper. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the slotted pin trigger release had too much friction to release with one hand quickly. Secondly, the linkages were arranged in such a way that energy would be lost at the launch. The linkages were inefficiently placed, and was probably overall a weaker and power-inefficient&amp;nbsp;design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="second-iteration"&gt;Second&amp;nbsp;Iteration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second iteration resolved the issue of the possibility of momentum being lost due to undesired angular rotation at the single axle by introducing two axles instead of one at the center joint, in addition to gearing the arms to constantly mesh them together. The arms were simplified and made much more rigid which significantly improved the design. At this stage, the leaper showed promising&amp;nbsp;results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought only one set of gears would suffice, but both top and bottom joints needed gears for optimal linear motion. This second iteration also deleted the slotted pin trigger, and instead allowed the linkages to fold past the maximum tension point, allowing the leaper to be in a constant tensile state. When ready to leap, the leaper would be balanced between the states of unfolding, and easily be nudged into its correct unfolding&amp;nbsp;motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="third-iteration-final-design"&gt;Third Iteration (Final&amp;nbsp;Design)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third iteration optimized launch angle at 60 degrees, widened the base so it would stand easier, gusseted the bottom center joint to reduce mass, and embiggened holes to affix lead mass to. I also added gears to the top joint, and filleted sharp corners of the gears due to a failure from the second iteration at a sharp&amp;nbsp;corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began to use Silly Putty to increase friction between the surface of the launch and the bottom center joint of the leaper, which had a better time adhering due to the gusseting. This third iteration proved to be successful at the two official&amp;nbsp;launches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressed for time, I decided to increase the tension and mass by moving the screws to the outer threads and adding more rubber bands and mass. I recorded my two official launches successfully, and the leaper&amp;nbsp;survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was beginning to see flexing in the 3D printed arms from the amount of tension that was stored in the rubber bands. Additionally, upon leaping, the two arms came together very hard and showed signs of chipping and damage. The design through use began to get a little bit flimsy and loose, so the non-geared joints could be redesigned to withstand more strength and impact against each other. Despite this, the leaper made two successful leaps and&amp;nbsp;survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="physical-description-of-operation"&gt;Physical Description of&amp;nbsp;Operation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final iteration of design 2 dubbed the &amp;#8220;stick leaper&amp;#8221; is 3D printed and rubber band powered. It works by propelling a mass of lead at a high velocity to generate momentum that will carry the entire stick leaper through the&amp;nbsp;trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lead mass is propelled by being affixed to the end of a pair of 3D printed folding arms. The arms are manually folded and tensioned with rubber bands, and when unfolded, propel the mass in a fast linear direction. The tensioned rubber bands are hooked around metric screws that are directly screwed into the folding arms. The tensioned rubber bands are held fast to the arms by a separate set of rubber bands wrapped around each pair of metric&amp;nbsp;screws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The folding motion of the arms is controlled by gearing the arms of the stick leaper so they move concurrently. The device is a bistable mechanism where the full folding motion extends just past the maximum rubber band tensile point, where the device can fall into a stable but tensioned&amp;nbsp;position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the final launch, 10 rubber bands were used for tensioning, and 4 were used to retain the rubber bands to the screws after&amp;nbsp;unfolding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="final-design-specifications"&gt;Final Design&amp;nbsp;Specifications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final design features:
- &lt;strong&gt;Launch angle&lt;/strong&gt;: 60 degrees
- &lt;strong&gt;Power source&lt;/strong&gt;: 10 rubber bands for tensioning, 4 for retention
- &lt;strong&gt;Mass&lt;/strong&gt;: Lead scraps affixed to the arms
- &lt;strong&gt;Trigger mechanism&lt;/strong&gt;: Bistable mechanism - balanced at tipping point, nudged to trigger
- &lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;: 3D printed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt; components with metal screws and copper rod&amp;nbsp;axles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="list-of-materials"&gt;List of&amp;nbsp;Materials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Material&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Amount&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3D Printed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;107.79 grams (final design only)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M4x0.7x10mm Screw&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8 pieces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rubber Bands&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14 pieces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1/16&amp;#8221; copper rod&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12 inches&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Silly Putty&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 pack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lead Scraps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4 ounces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$8.16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons&amp;nbsp;Learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project taught me valuable lessons about:
- Iterative design and prototyping
- The importance of testing and refinement
- Working within constraints (budget, materials, safety)
- 3D printing considerations for mechanical parts
- Energy transfer and mechanical advantage in linkage&amp;nbsp;systems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project successfully demonstrated the engineering design process from problem definition through multiple iterations to a working&amp;nbsp;solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="source-documents"&gt;Source&amp;nbsp;Documents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following documents are available for&amp;nbsp;reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2022/cad-project/CAD-Project-Final-Report.pdf"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; Project Final Report&lt;/a&gt; - Complete final report with design process, iterations, and&amp;nbsp;analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2022/cad-project/DesignProjectAssignment8ProgressReport056.pdf"&gt;Progress Report 056&lt;/a&gt; - Early progress&amp;nbsp;documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2022/cad-project/DesignProjectAssignment8ProgressReport057.pdf"&gt;Progress Report 057&lt;/a&gt; - Mid-project progress&amp;nbsp;update&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/documents/2022/cad-project/DesignProjectAssignment8ProgressReport058.pdf"&gt;Progress Report 058&lt;/a&gt; - Final progress&amp;nbsp;documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This project was completed in November 2022 for Intro to Engineering (Professor Khandani) as part of my personal engineering&amp;nbsp;coursework.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="School Projects"/><category term="cad"/><category term="design"/><category term="engineering"/><category term="school-project"/><category term="fusion360"/><category term="3d-printing"/></entry></feed>